It's really, really great to be here.
إنه لمن الرائع حقاً، حقاً أن أكون هنا.
You have the power to change the world.
أنتم لديكم القدرة على تغيير العالم.
I’m not saying that to be cliché,
أنا لا أقول ذلك بشكل مبتذل،
you really have the power to change the world.
أنت حقاً لديك القدرة على تغيير العالم.
Deep inside of you, every single one of you
بداخل كل شخص منكم
has the most powerful device known to man.
هناك أقوى جهاز عرفه الإنسان.
And that's an idea.
وهو الفكرة.
So a single idea, from the human mind,
فكرة واحدة، من العقل البشري،
it could start a groundswell,
قد تكون بداية لعاصفة،
it could be a flash point for a movement
أو شرارة انطلاق،
and it can actually rewrite our future.
وربما تعمل على إعادة تشكيل مستقبلنا.
But an idea is powerless
ولكن الفكرة تكون بلا جدوى
if it stays inside of you.
لو بقيت محبوسة داخلك.
If you never pull that idea out for others to contend with,
لو لم تظهر تلك الفكرة للمنافسة مع الآخرين،
it will die with you.
ستموت معك.
Now, maybe some of you guys have tried to convey your idea
ربما حاول بعضكم توصيل فكرته
and it wasn't adopted, it was rejected,
لكن لم يتم قبولها، وتم رفضها،
and some other mediocre or average idea was adopted.
في حين تم قبول بعض الأفكار العادية.
And the only difference between those two is in the way it was communicated.
والفرق الوحيد بين الفكرتين هو طريقة توصيلهما.
Because if you communicate an idea in a way that resonates,
لأنك لو قمت بإيصال فكرتك بطريقة يتردد صداها،
change will happen, and you can change the world.
سيحدث ذلك تغيراً، ومن ثم ستغير العالم.
In my family, we collect these vintage European posters.
تجمع أسرتي الملصقات الأوروبية القديمة.
Every time we go to Maui, we go to the dealer there,
في كل مرة نسافر إلى ماوي، نذهب إلى تاجر هناك،
and he turns these great big posters.
يُظهر لنا هذه الملصقات الكبيرة.
I love them. They all have one idea
أحب الملصقات. جميعها تحوي فكرة واحدة
and one really clear visual that conveys the idea.
ولديها رؤية بصرية واضحة توصل الفكرة.
They are about the size of a mattress. They're really big.
فهي بحجم الفراش تقريبًا وضخمة جدًا.
They're not as thick as a mattress, but they're big.
فهي ليست بسماكة الفراش، إلا إنها ضخمة.
And the guy will tell the story as he turns the pages.
يخبرك الرجل بالقصة ويقلب الصفحات.
And this one time I was flanked by my two kids
وهذه المره كنت محاطة بطفليي
and he turns the page and this poster is underneath,
وقام بقلب الصفحة وهذا الملصق تحته
and right when I lean forward and say,
وعندها انحنيت للأمام وقُلت،
"Oh my God, I love this poster,"
" ياإلهي، أنا أُحب هذا الملصق،"
both of my kids jumped back and they are like,
قفز طفلييّ للوراء وقالا:
"Oh my God, mom, it's you."
" يا إلهي، ماما، إنها أنتِ."
And this is the poster.
وهذا هو الملصق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
See, I'm like "Fire it up!"
ترون، كأنني أقول "أشعلوا المكان!"
The thing I loved about this poster was the irony.
ما أحببته في هذا الملصق هو التهكم.
Here's this chick all fired up, headed into battle --
هذه السيدة في غاية الحماس، متوجهة للمعركة...
as the standard bearer --
كما يُظهر العمود.
and she's holding these little Suavitos baking spices,
وتُمسك في يدها توابل السافيتوس للخَبز،
like something so seemingly insignificant,
ويظهر أنه أمر ليس ذي أهمية،
though she's willing to risk, you know, life and limb to promote this thing.
على الرغم من أنها مستعدة للمخاطرة بحياتها وأطرافها للترويج لهذا الشيء،
So if you are to swap out those little Suavitos baking spices
لو قمتم باستبدال توابل السافيتوس هذه
with a presentation --
بعرضٍ حي...
Yeah, it's me, pretty fired up.
سأكون أنا البديل في غاية الحماس.
I was fired up about presentations
كنتُ شغوفة بشأن العروض
back when it wasn't cool to be fired up about presentations.
حين كان الشغف بالعروض ليس أمراً جيداً.
I really think they have the power to change the world
أنا مؤمنة حقًا أن الأفكار تملك القدرة على تغيير العالم
when you communicate effectively through them.
عندما يتم توصيلها بشكل فعال.
And changing the world is hard.
وأن تغيير العالم أمر صعب.
It won't happen with just one person with one single idea.
وأن ذلك التغيير لن يحدثه شخص واحد وفكرة واحدة.
That idea has got to spread, or it won't be effective.
تلك الفكرة يجب أن تُتشر، وإلا لن تكون فعالة.
So it has to come out of you
لذا ينبغي إظهارها
and out into the open for people to see.
للخارج، ليراها الناس.
And the way that ideas are conveyed the most effectively is through story.
وأفضل طريقة لتوصيل الأفكار هي من خلال القصة.
You know, for thousands of years,
تعلمون، منذ آلاف السنين،
illiterate generations would pass on their values and their culture
قامت الأجيال الأُمية بنقل قيمها وثقافتها
from generation to generation,
من جيل إلى جيل،
and they would stay intact.
وبقيت تلك القيم سالمة كما هي
So there's something kind of magical about a story structure
هناك شيء ما سحري في تركيبة القصة
that makes it so that when it's assembled,
مما يجعلها عند تجميعها
it can be ingested and then recalled
سهلة التلقي ومن ثم التذكر
by the person who's receiving it.
من قبل المُتلقي.
So basically a story, you get a physical reaction;
في القصه تحصل على رد فعل جسدي
your heart can race, your eyes can dilate,
تتسارع نبضات قلبك، يتوسع بؤبؤ عينك،
you could talk about, "Oh, I got a chill down my spine"
قد تقول "لقد اقشعر أسفل عمودي الفقري"
or, "I could feel it in the pit of my stomach."
او" لقد شعرت به كأنه في تجويف معدتي."
We actually physically react when someone is telling us a story.
نحن فعلاً نتفاعل جسدياً حينما يخبرنا شخص ما قصة.
So even though the stage is the same, a story can be told,
وبالرغم من أن المسرح الذي تسرد، القصة عبره هو نفسه،
but once a presentation is told, it completely flatlines.
ولكن بمجرد وضعها في عرض، تصبح القصة ميتة تماماً.
And I wanted to figure out why.
لذا أردت معرفة السبب.
Why is it that we physically sit with rapt attention during a story,
لماذا نكون جسدياً في حالة اهتمام مُغرِق خلال القصة،
but it just dies for a presentation.
ونفقد ذلك الإحساس عند وضعها في عرض.
So I wanted to figure out, how do you incorporate story into presentations.
لذلك أردت معرفة كيفية دمج القصة في العرض.
So we've had thousands of presentations back at the shop --
لذلك كان لدينا الآلاف من العروض السابقة في المعرض.
hundreds of thousands of presentations, actually,
مئات الآلاف من العروض، في الحقيقة،
so I knew the context of a really bad presentation.
لذلك كنت أعرف المحتوى السيىء لأي عرض.
I decided to study cinema and literature,
لقد قررت أن أدرس السينما والأدب،
and really dig in and figure out what was going on
ووالقيام بالبحث ومعرفة السبب
and why it was broken.
وما هو سبب الفشل.
So, I want to show you some of the findings
سأريكم بعض النتائج
that led up to what I've uncovered as a presentation form.
التي تقود لمعرفة شكل العرض.
So it was obvious to start with Aristotle,
كان من الطبيعي أن نبدأ مع ارسطو،
he had a three-act structure, a beginning, a middle and an end.
كان لديه بنية ثلاثية، البداية والوسط والنهاية.
We studied poetics and rhetoric,
درسنا الشعر والبلاغة،
and a lot of presentations don't even have that in its most simple form.
فالكثير من العروض لا تحتوي على ذلك حتى في أبسط أشكالها.
And then when I moved on to studying hero archetypes,
وعندما تقدمت لدراسة نماذج الأبطال،
I thought, "OK, the presenter is the hero,
اعتقدت أن، "حسناً، المقدم هو البطل،
they're up on the stage, they're the star of the show."
إنه على خشبة المسرح، إنه نجم العرض."
It's easy to feel, as the presenter, that you're the star of the show.
من السهل، كمقدم للعرض، أن تشعر أنك نجم العرض.
I realized right away, that that's really broken.
أدركتُ على الفور، أن ذلك كان خاطئاً.
Because I have an idea, I can put it out there,
لأنه لدي فكرة، يمكنني توصيلها،
but if you guys don't grab that idea and hold it as dear,
ولكن إن لم تفهموا هذه الفكرة ولم تقدروها حق قدرها،
the idea goes nowhere and the world is never changed.
فإن هذه الفكرة تبقى حبيسة وأن العالم لا يتغيير ابداً.
So in reality, the presenter isn't the hero,
ولذلك في الواقع، المقدم ليس هو البطل،
the audience is the hero of our idea.
الجمهور هو البطل أفكارنا.
So if you look at Joseph Campbell's hero's journey,
لذلك لو نظرتم إلى رحلة البطل جوزيف كامبل،
just in the front part, there were some really interesting insights there.
في الجزء الأول فقط، كانت هناك بعض الأفكار المثيرة للاهتمام.
So there is this likable hero in an ordinary world,
فهناك البطل المحبوب في العالم العادي
and they get this call to adventure.
وهذا محفز للوجود المغامرة.
So the world is kind of brought out of balance.
لذلك فالعالم يُظهر نوعا من عدم التوازن.
And at first they're resistant.
في البداية يقاومون.
They're like, "I don't know if I want to jump into this,"
ويقولون، "لا أعلم إن كنت أريد المجازفة في هذه الأمر،"
and then a mentor comes along
ثم يأتي المرشد
and helps them move from their ordinary world
ويساعدهم على التحول من العالم العادي
into a special world.
إلى عالمهم الخاص.
And that's the role of the presenter.
وهذا هو دور مقدم العرض.
It's to be the mentor. You're not Luke Skywalker, you're Yoda.
أن تكون المرشد. فأنت لست لوك سكاي والكر، بل أنت المعلم يودا.
You're the one that actually helps the audience
أنت الشخص الذي يساعد الجمهور
move from one thing and into your new special idea,
للتحرك من الفكرة الثابتة إلى فكرتك الخاصة الجديدة،
and that's the power of a story.
وهذه هي مصدر قوة القصة.
So in its most simple structure, it's a three-part structure of a story.
تتكون القصة في أبسط صورها من ثلاث أجزاء.
You have a likable hero who has a desire,
هناك بطل محبوب ولديه رغبة
they encounter a roadblock
يواجه البطل المصاعب
and ultimately they emerge, transform, and that's the basic structure.
ثم تظهر هذه المصاعب وتتحول وهذا هو الهيكل البسيط للقصة.
But it wasn't until I came across a Gustav Freytag's pyramid --
استمر هذا إلى أن وجدت هرم جوستاف فريتاج ...
he drew this shape in 1863.
رسمه على هذا الشكل في عام 1863.
Now, he was a German dramatist ...
هو درامي ألماني...
he was a German dramatist
لقد كان درامياً ألمانياً
and he believed there is a five-act structure,
أعتقد أن هناك خمس هياكل عمل
which has an exposition, a rising action,
وهي العرض وتصعيد العمل
a climax, a falling action and a denouement,
والذروة وتهدأة العمل وحل عقدة القصة.
which is the unraveling or the resolution of the story.
و الذي هو كشف أو حل القصة في النهاية.
I love this shape. So we talk about shapes.
أحب هذا الشكل. لذلك نتحدث عن الأشكال.
A story has an arc -- well, an arc is a shape.
لدى القصة منحى... حسناً، المنحى هو شكل كذلك.
We talk about classical music having a shapeliness to it.
نتكلم عن الموسيقى الكلاسيكية، لديها شكل الجملون.
So I thought, hey, if presentations had a shape,
فلو كان للعروض التقديمية شكلاً.
what would that shape be?
فكيف يكون ذلك الشكل؟
And how did the greatest communicators use that shape,
وكيف استخدم المتحدثون العظماء ذلك الشكل؟
or do they use a shape?
أو هل يستخدمون شكلاً؟
So I'll never forget, it was a Saturday morning.
لذلك لن أنسى أبداً لقد كان صباح يوم السبت.
After all this study -- it was a couple of years of study --
بعد كل تلك الدراسة... لقد كانا عامين من الدراسة...
I drew a shape.
رسمت شكلاً.
And I was like, "Oh my gosh, if this shape is real,
وكنت مثل، "يالهي، لو كان هذا الشكل حقيقيا،
I should be able to take two completely different presentations
سأتمكن من أخذ عرضين تقديمياً مختلفين تماماً
and overlay it, and it should be true."
وأقوم بدراستهما، ويجب أن يكونا حقيقين."
So I took the obvious,
لذلك أخذت العرض الواضح،
I took Martin Luther King's "I Have a Dream" speech,
أخذت خطاب مارتن لوثر كينج "لدي حلم".
and I took Steve Jobs' 2007 iPhone launch speech,
وأخذت خطاب إطلاق أيفون 2007 لستيف جوبز،
I overlaid it over it, and it worked.
دمجت كلهما معاً و نجح الأمر.
I sat in my office, just astounded.
جلست في مكتبي مدهوشة.
I actually cried a little,
بكيت بالفعل قليلاً.
because I was like, "I've been given this gift,"
لأنني كنت مثل: "لقد رزقت بهذه الموهبة."
and here it is,
وها هي،
this is the shape of a great presentation.
هذا هو شكل العرض التقديمي الرائع.
Isn't it amazing?
أليس ذلك مدهشاً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was crying.
كنت أبكي.
I want to walk you through it, it's pretty astounding.
أود شرحه لكم، إنه مذهل.
There is a beginning, a middle and an end, and I want to walk you through it.
هناك بداية، ووسط، ونهاية، وسأشرحها لكم.
Because the greatest communicators -- I went through speeches, everything --
لأن المتحدثين العظماء الذين درست حديثهم،
I can overlay the shape.
يمكنني عرض الشكل.
Even the Gettysburg Address follows the shape.
حتى نموذج جيتسبرج يتبع هذا الشكل.
At the beginning of any presentation, you need to establish what is.
في بداية أي عرض تقديمي، تحتاج لأن توضح.
You know, here's the status quo, here's what's going on.
هناك الوضع الراهن، هذا هو صلب الموضوع
And then you need to compare that to what could be.
ومن ثم تقارن ذلك بما يمكن أن يحدث لاحقاً.
You need to make that gap as big as possible,
فأنت بحاجة إلى توسيع الفجوة بقدر الإمكان،
because there is this commonplace of the status quo,
لأن هناك نوع شائع من الوضع الراهن،
and you need to contrast that with the loftiness of your idea.
وأنت بحاجة لتقارن ذلك مع فكرتك.
So it's like, you know, here's the past, here's the present,
هو مثل، أن هنا الماضي، وهنا الحاضر،
but look at our future.
ولكنك تفكر في المستقبل.
Here's a problem, but look at that problem removed.
هنا المعضلة، وترى تلك المشكلة تحل.
Here's a roadblock, let's annihilate the roadblock.
هنا حجرة العثرة دعنا نزيل هذا الحجر.
You need to really amplify that gap.
أنت بحاجة لأن توسع تلك الفجوة.
This would be like the inciting incident in a movie.
هذا مثل حادث في فيلم.
That's when suddenly the audience has to contend
فيقوم الجمهور التفاعل
with what you just put out there:
مع ما عرضته عليهم:
"Wow, do I want to agree with this and align with it or not?"
"آه، هل أود الموافقة على ذلك أم لا؟"
And in the rest of your presentation should support that.
وفي بقية عرضك تعمل على تدعيم ذلك.
So the middle goes back and forth,
فوسط العرض يتأرجح إلى الأمام والخلف
it traverses between what is and what could be,
فينتقل ما بين الوضع الحالي وما ينبغي أن يكون،
what is and what could be.
مابين الكائن والممكن.
Because what you are trying to do
لأن ما تحاول فعله
is make the status quo and the normal unappealing,
الحالي وحالته السيئة،
and you're wanting to draw them
وأنت تود أخذهم للمستقبل عندما
towards what could be in the future with your idea adopted.
يتبنون فكرتك.
Now, on your way to change the world, people are going to resist.
الآن، في طريقك لتغيير العالم، سيقاوم الناس
They're not going to be excited, they may love the world the way it is.
لن يتحمسوا، ربما يعجبهم الوضع كما
So you'll encounter resistance.
هو عليه. لذا ستواجه مقاومتهم.
That's why you have to move back and forth.
لذا عليك التحرك للأمام وللخلف.
It's similar to sailing.
يشبه الأمر الإبحار.
When you're sailing against the wind and there is wind resistance,
عندما تبحر عكس الرياح فتقاومك،
you have to move your boat back and forth, and back and forth.
عليك تحريك قالبك للأمام والخلف، أمام وخلف.
That's so you can capture the wind.
تفعل ذلك لتلحق بالرياح.
You have to actually capture the resistance
عليك في الواقع أن تلحق بالمقاومة
coming against you when you're sailing.
عندما تأتي باتجاهك بينما تبحر.
Now interesting, if you capture the wind just right
من المثير أنك لو لحقت بالرياح بشكل صحيح
and you set your sail just right,
وعدلت شراعك بشكل صحيح
your ship will actually sail faster than the wind itself.
ستبحر سفينك أسرع من الرياح نفسها.
It is a physics phenomenon.
إنها ظاهرة فيزيائية.
So by planting in there
وبتطبيق ذلك
the way they're going to resist between what is and what can be,
مقاومتهم لما هو موجود وما يمكن وجوده،
is actually going to draw them towards your idea
سيدفعهم في الواقع باتجاه فكرتك
quicker than should you not do that.
أسرع مما كنت ستفعله.
So after you've moved back and forth between what is and what could be,
إذًا، بعد تحركك بين الموجود وما يمكن،
the last turning point is a call to action,
آخر شيء هو دعوة للعمل.
which every presentation should have, but at the very end.
والتي توجد بكل عرض تقديمي، ولكن في نهايته.
You need to describe the world as a new bliss.
عليك ان تصف العالم كنعمة جديدة.
"This is utopia with my idea adopted."
"ستتحقق يوتوبيا عندما تُنفذ فكرتي."
"This is the way the world is going to look,
"سيبدو العالم بتلك الطريقة،
when we join together and we solve this big problem."
عندما نتعاون لحل تلك المشكلة."
You need to use that as your ending,
عليك استخدام ذلك كخاتمة لعرضك،
in a very poetic and dramatic way.
بطريقة شاعرية ودرامية.
So, interestingly, when I was done,
من المثير أنني عندما انتهيت، قلت،
I was like, "You know what? I could use this as an analysis tool."
"أتعلمين؟ يمكن استخدام ذلك كأداة تحليل."
I actually transcribe speeches,
أنا أفرغ المحادثات صوتيًٍا في الواقع،
and I would actually map out, how much they map to this tool.
وسأوضح كيف يتبعون تلك الطريقة.
So I want to show you some of that today,
لذا سأعرض بعضها اليوم.
and I want to start with the very two people
وأود البدء باثنين حللت
that I used when I first did.
محادثتهم عندما بدأت.
Here's Mr. Jobs, has completely changed the world.
ها هو السيد جوبز، غيّر العالم تمامًا.
Changed the world of personal computing, changed the music industry
غيّر عالم الحواسيب، غيّر صناعة الموسيقى
and now he's on his way to change the mobile device industry.
والآن في طريقه لتغيير صناعة الهواتف.
So he's definitely changed the world.
لذا فهو بالتأكيد غيّر العالم.
And this is the shape of his iPhone launch 2007,
وهذا هو شكل أيفون الذي أطلقه في 2007،
when he launched his iPhone.
عندما أطلق هذا الأيفون.
It's a 90-minute talk and you can see he starts with what is,
محادثته لمدة 90 دقيقة، وقد بدأ بعرض الوضع
traverses back and forth and ends with what could be.
الحالي، انتقل للأمام والخلف وختم بالممكن.
So I want to zoom in on this:
أود التعمق في ذلك:
the white line is him speaking, he's talking.
الخط الأبيض بعبر عنه وهو يتحدث.
The next color line you'll see popped up there,
الخط التالي ها هو هناك،
that's when he cuts to video.
إنه عندما أوقف الفيديو.
So he's adding some variety and he cuts to demo.
قام بإضافة بعض الأشياء
So it's not just him talking the whole time.
لذا فهو لا يتحدث وحده طوال الوقت.
And these lines are representative there.
وتمثل تلك الخطوط هناك.
And then towards the end you'll see a blue line,
وقُرب النهاية سترى خطًا أزرقًا،
which will be the guest speaker.
وهو يعبر عن متحدث آخر.
So this is where it gets kind of interesting:
هناك تصبح الأمور مثيرة نوعًا:
every tick mark here is when he made them laugh.
كل علامة هنا تعبر عن إضحاكه لهم.
And every tick mark here is when he made them clap.
وكل علامة هنا عندما جعلهم يصفقون.
They are so involved physically,
إنهم مندمجين بأجسادهم تمامًا.
they are physically reacting to what he is saying,
إنهم يستجيبون جسديًا لما يقوله،
which is actually fantastic,
وهو شيء رائع حقًا،
because then you know you have the audience in your hand.
لأنك تعرف وقتها أن الجمهور بين يديك.
So he kicks off what could be with,
اذًا فقد بدأ بما يمكن وجوده،
"This is a day I've been looking forward to for two and a half years."
"كنت أنتظر ذلك اليوم من سنتين ونصف."
So he is launching a product
لذا فهو يطلق منتج
that he's known about already for a couple of years.
عرف بشأنه منذ سنتين.
So this is not a new product to him.
إنه ليس منتجًا جديدًا له.
But look at this,
ولكن انظر لذلك
he does this other thing: he marvels.
إنه يفعل شيئًا آخر، إنه يتعجب.
He marvels at his own product.
ينبهر بمنتجه الخاص.
He marvels himself more than the audience laughs or claps.
إنه منبهر أكثر من الجمهور الذي يصفق ويضحك.
So he is like, "Isn't this awesome? Isn't this beautiful?"
كأنه يقول،"أليس ذلك رائعًا؟ أو ليس جميلًا؟"
He is modeling for the audience what he wants them to feel.
إنه يمثل للجمهور ما يريدهم أن يشعروا به.
So he is actually doing a job of compelling them to feel a certain way.
لذا فهو يجبرهم نوعًا على الشعور بشيء ما.
So he kicks off with what could be with, "Every once in a while,
لذا فهو يذكرهم بما يمكن وجوده كل فترة،
a revolutionary product comes along that changes everything."
منتج ثوري سيغير كل شيء."
So he starts to kick in and talk about his new product.
لذا يبدأ بالحديث عن منتجه الجديد.
Now, at the beginning of it, he actually keeps the phone off.
الآن، في البداية، فهو يبقي الهاتف مغلقًا.
You'll see that the line is pretty white up until this point,
سترى الخط أبيضًا حتي تلك النقطة،
so he goes off between,
لذا فهو ينتقل ما بين،
"Here's this new phone, and here's the sucky competitors.
"الهاتف الجديد، والهواتف الأخرى المزعجة.
Here's this new phone, and here's the sucky competitors."
الهاتف الجديد، والهواتف الأخرى المزعجة."
And then, right about here, he has the star moment --
ثم، هنا تحديدًا، يحظى بأهم لحظة..
and that something we'll always remember.
وهي لحظة سنتذكرها دومًا.
He turns the phone on.
يقوم بتشغيل الهاتف.
The audience sees scrolling for the first time,
يري الجمهور لأول مرة التمرير لأول مرة،
you can hear the oxygen sucked out of the room.
يمكنك سماع الأكسجين يُسحب من الغرفة.
They gasped. You can actually hear it.
كانوا يلهثون. يمكنك سماع ذلك.
So he creates a moment that they'll always remember.
إنه يفعل شيئًا سيذكرونه دائمًا.
So if we move along this model, you can see the blue,
لو نظرنا للرسم، يمكنك رؤية اللون الأزرق،
where the external speakers are going,
حيث يتحدث الآخرون،
and towards the bottom right, the line breaks.
وقرب الطرف السفلي الأيمن، ينكسر الخط.
That's because his clicker broke.
هذا لأن جهاز العرض تعطل.
He wants to keep this heightened sense of excitement.
يود الإبقاء على حماسته.
He tells a personal story,
فيحكي قصة شخصية،
right there, where the technology didn't work.
هناك حيث لم تنفع التكنولوجيا.
So he's the master communicator,
لذا فهو المتحدث الأعظم،
and he turns to story to keep the audience involved.
ويحكي قصة للإبقاء على تركيز جمهوره.
So the top right he ends with the new bliss.
هناك بالأعلى نحو اليمين يتحدث عن منتجه.
He leaves them with the promise
يتركهم واعدًا إياهم
that Apple will continue to build revolutionary new products.
بأن شركة أبل ستنتج منتجات أخرى ثورية.
And he says,
ويقول،
We've always tried to do that at Apple since the very beginning
نحاول فعل ذلك في أبل منذ البداية
and we always will."
وسنستمر بذلك."
So he ends with the new bliss.
وينهي بالمنتج العظيم الجديد.
So let's look at Mr. King.
فلننظر للسيد كينج.
He was an amazing visionary, a clergyman
كانت لديه رؤية،
who spent his life working hard for equality.
وقضى حياته يعمل من أجل المساواة.
And this is the shape of the "I Have a Dream" speech.
وهذا هو شكل محادثته "لدي حلم".
You can see he starts with what is,
يمكنك رؤية أنه بدأ الحديث عما يوجد،
moves back and forth between what is and what could be,
يتحرك بين الموجود و بين ما يمكن تحقيقه،
and ends with a very poetic new bliss, which is the famous part we all know.
وينهي بنعمة شاعرية، الجزء الذي نعرفه كلنا.
So I'm going to spread it out a little bit here,
سأقوم بعرضه قليلاً هنا
stretch it for you,
أقدمه لكم
and what I'm doing here is I put the actual transcript there
وما أفعله هو أني أضع التفريغ الصوتي هناك
along with the text.
بمحاذاة النص.
I know you can't read it.
أعلم أنه لا يمكن قراءته.
But at the end of every line break, I broke the line,
ولكن بنهاية كل خط، كسرت الخط،
because he took a breath and he paused.
لأنه تنفس وأوقف الحديث.
Now he was a Southern Baptist preacher, most people hadn't heard that,
كان واعظًا جنوبيًا، لم يعرف المعظم ذلك،
so he had a real cadence and a rhythm that was really new for people there.
لذا كان لديه ايقاع حقيقي جديد عن الناس هنا
So I want to cover up these lines of text with a bar
لذا، أردت أن أخفي تلك الخطوط بشريط
because I want to use this bar as an information device here.
لأني أردت إستخدام هذا الشريط كطريقة للمعلومات هنا
So let's walk through how he actually spoke to the people.
لذا دعونا نعرف كيف خطب في الناس
The blue bars here are going to be when he used
الشريط الأزرق هنا سيكون عندما استخدم
the actual rhetorical device of repetition.
طريقة بلاغية للتكرار.
So he was repeating himself,
لذا عندما كان يكرر كلامه،
he was using the same words and phrases,
كان يستخدم نفس الكلمات والعبارات،
so people could remember and recall them.
لذا يستطيع الناس تذكرها.
But then he also used a lot of metaphors and visual words.
حينها يستخدم الكثير من الاستعارات والصور الجمالية.
This was a way to take really complicated ideas
كانت طريقة لعرض الأفكار المعقدة
and make them memorable and knowledgeable, so people got it.
وجعلها سهلة التذكر والفهم، فيفهمها الناس.
He actually created very --
ابتكر حقا..
almost like scenes with his words to make it
مشاهد مصورة بكلماته
so they could envision what he was saying.
فيستطيعون تخيل ما يقول.
And then there were also a lot of familiar songs and scriptures that he used.
واستخدم أيضاً العديد من الأغاني والسيناريوهات المألوفة
This is just the front end of it that you're seeing.
تلك فقط الواجهة الأمامية مما تراه.
And then he also made a lot of political references
إبتكر أيضاً العديد من المراجع السياسية
of the promises that were made to the people.
للوعود التي أقروها على الناس.
So if we look at the very first end of what is,
لذا إذا نظرنا لأول نهاية لذلك
at the very end of what is was the very first time
في أول نهاية لذلك، كانت أول مرة
that people actually clapped and roared really loud.
حين صفق الناس بحرارة وهللوا بصوت عالي
So the end of what is what he did is he said,
لذا كان آخر شيء فعله هو قوله:
"America has given the Negro people a bad check,
"حين أعطت أمريكا قرض كبير للأشخاص السود،
a check which has come back marked insufficient funds."
والذي تسبب بنقص الأموال".
Well, everyone knows what it's like to not have money in your account.
حسناً، يعرف الجميع شعور: عدم وجود مال في حسابك.
So he used the metaphor people were very familiar with.
لذا استخدم استعارة مألوفة للناس.
But when they really charged up,
لكن عندما اتُهموا،
the very first time they really screamed was:
لأول مرة، انفعلوا قائلين:
"So we have come to cash this check,
"لذا علينا أن نرد القرض
a check that will give us upon demand
قرض يعطينا حسب الطلب،
the riches of freedom and the security of justice."
ثروات الحرية وأمن العدالة".
That's when they really clapped.
هنا حين صفقوا بحرارة.
It was when he compared what currently is to what could be.
ذلك حين قارن بين الوضع الحالي وبين المفترض أن يكون.
So when we move along a little farther in the model,
إذا انتقلنا قليلاً في هذا النموذج،
you'll see it goes back and forth at a more frenzied pace.
نرى أنه يتحرك ذهاباً و إياباً بمعدل أكثر سرعة.
And this is when he goes back and forth, and back and forth.
وهذا حين تحرك ذهاباً وإياباً، وذهاباً وإياباً.
Now the audience was in a frenzy.
أصبح الجمهور الآن متحمسين للغاية،
They were all excited, and so you can actually do this
كانوا جميعهم متحمسين، لذا يمكنك القيام بذلك حقا
to keep them in a heightened sense of excitement.
لجعلهم في أقصى مراحل الحماس
So he says, "I have a dream
لذا قال: "لدي حلم
that one day this nation will rise up and live out the meaning of its creed.
بأن في يوم ما ستنهض الأمة وتعيش بها معنى عقيدتها
'We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal.'"
نعرف تلك الحقائق لنكون شهداء على أن جميع البشر متساوون".
So he uses the little orange text there to remind them of the promise
استخدم النص البرتقالي هناك لتذكرتهم بالوعد
that the politicians had made to him or that this country had made.
الذي وعده به السياسيون أو الذي وعدته به البلاد
Then he moves back and forth between
ثم تحرك ذهاباً وإياباً بين
"I have a dream that one day, I have a dream that one day,
"لدي حلم بأنه يوماً ما، لدي حلم بأنه يوماً ما،
I have a dream that one day,"
لدي حلم بأنه يوما ما"
and at the end, it gets really interesting.
وفي النهاية أصبح شيقا حقا
Because he uses -- you can look at the four shades of green,
لأنه إستخدم بإمكااكم النظر للخانة الخضراء الرابعة
there's a lot of blue there, which was a lot of repetition --
يوجد الكثير من الأزرق هنا حيث يوجد الكثير من التكرار
he had a heightened sense of repetition.
كان لديه حس عالي من التكرار
And the green was a heightened sense of songs and scriptures.
والأخضر كان حس عالي من الأغاني و الترانيم
So the first batch of green
إذاً أول خط أخضر
was the actual scripture from the Book of Isaiah.
كانت ترنيمة حقيقية من كتاب أشعياء
The second batch of green was "My Country, 'Tis of Thee."
ثاني خط أخضر كان "بلادي، النشيد الوطني".
Now, that's a familiar song that was specifically very significant
الآن، تلك أغنية مألوفة ومهمة على وجه التحديد
for the black people at the time,
للأشخاص السود فى ذلك الوقت،
because this song was the song they chose to change the words to as an outcry,
لأنها كانت الأغنية التي اختاروها لتغيير الكلمات كنوع من الاحتجاج،
saying that promises had not been kept.
لقول أن الوعود لم تُنفذ
So the third batch of green was actually a stanza from "My Country, 'Tis of Thee."
لذا ثالث خط أخضر كان مقطع من "بلادي، النشيد الوطني الأمريكي"
And then the fourth was a Negro spiritual.
والرابع كان روح سوداء
"Free at last! Free at last! Thank God Almighty, I'm free at last!"
"حر في النهاية، حر في انهاية حمداً لله، أنا حر في النهاية"
So what he did is he actually reached inside of the hearts of the audience.
إذاً ما فعله هو أنه وصل حقاً لقلوب الجمهور.
He pulled from scriptures, which is important.
اقتبس من الكتاب المقدس، وذلك مهم
He pulled from songs that they'd sung together
اقتبس من الأغاني التي ينشدوها معاً
as an outcry against this outrage,
كصرخة ضد الغضب
and he used those as a device to connect and resonate with the audience.
وإستخدمهم كأداة للإتصال بالجمهور والتأثير فيهم
Ending -- painting a picture of this new bliss,
في النهاية، رسم لصورة لتلك النعمة الجديدة
using the very things inside of them that they already held as sacred.
مستغل تلك الأشياء المقدسة بداخلهم
So he was a great man. He had a big, big dream.
لذلك كان كينج رجلا عظيما. كان لديه حلم كبير جداً.
There's a lot of people here, you guys have really big dreams.
يوجد الكثير من الناس هنا، أنتم أيها الشباب لديكم أحلام كبيرة.
You have really big ideas inside of you
لديكم أفكار عظيمة بداخل كل منكم
that you need to get out.
تحتاج أن تنطلق للخارج.
But you know what? We encounter hardships.
و لكن أتعلم ماذا؟ نقابل مصاعب.
It's not easy to change the world;
ليس من السهل تغيير العالم:
it's a big job.
إنها مهمة عظيمة.
You know he was --
أتعلم كان...
his house was bombed, he was stabbed with a letter opener,
تم تفجير بيته، وتم طعنه بفتاحة رسائل،
ultimately, he lost his life,
في النهاية، خسر حياتة،
you know, for what he cared about.
أتعلم ، بما إهتم
But a lot of us aren't going to be required to pay that kind of sacrifice.
لكن الكثير منا غير مستعد لتقديم ذلك النوع من التضحية
But what happens is
لكن ماذا حدث
that it basically is a little bit like that basic story structure.
إنها ببساطة كانت مثل البنية الأساسية للقصة إلى حداً ما
Life can be like that.
كان ممكن أن تصبح الحياة هكذا
You know, you guys are all likable people,
أتعلمون إنكم جميعاً أشخاص محبوبون
you have a desire, you encounter roadblocks,
لديكم رغبة، واجهتم عواقب
and we stop there.
وتتوقفون عندها
We're just like, you know, "I had this idea,
أتعلمون إنكم مثل: "لدي تلك الفكرة
but I'm not going to put it out there.
لكني لن استخدمها
It's been rejected."
إنها مرفوضة"
You know, we self-sabotage our own ideas,
أتعلمون إننا المخربون لأفكارنا،
we just butt up against the roadblocks and butt up against the roadblocks
فقط يجب أن نمنع تلك العواقب ونمنع العواقب
instead of choosing to let the struggle transform us
بدلاًمن السماح لها بأن تغيرنا
and choosing to go ahead and have a dream and make it real.
واختيار أن نتقدم ونملك حلم لجعله واقعا
And you know, if anyone -- if I can do this, anybody can do this.
وتعلمون بأن أي شخص إذا بإمكاني فعل ذلك، إذاً بإمكان أي شخص آخر
I was raised in an economically and emotionally starved environment.
لقد نشأت في بيئة فقيرة مادياً ومعنوياً
First time I got to go to a camp with my sister, I was abused.
اول مرة ذهبت للمخيم مع أختى، تعرضت للتنمر
Wasn't the first time I was abused, it was just the most aggressive.
لم تكن أول مرة، لكنها كانت الأكثر عنفاً
And my mom and dad -- they married each other three times,
وتزوج أبي وأمي ثلاث مرات
(Audience murmurs)
(همهمات الجمهور)
Yeah, that was tumultuous, and when they weren't fighting
نعم كان ذلك مريعاً، وعندما كانوا يتشاجرون
they were helping sober up some alcoholic that was living with us
يقيظون مدمني الكحول الذين يعيشون معنا
because they were both sober alcoholics.
لأن كليهما كانا معالجين لإدمان الكحول
So my mom abandoned us when I was sixteen years old.
هجرتنا أمنا عندما كان عمري 16 عام
And I took on a role of caretaker of my home and of my siblings.
وتوليت مسؤولية البيت وأشقائي
And I married. I met a man.
وتزوجت، التقيت برجل
Fell in love. I went to a year of college.
وقعت في حبه، وذهبت للجامعة لمدة عام
I did what every single, bright, young girl should do --
فعلت ما يمكن أن تفعله كل شابة عزباء واعدة
I got married when I was eighteen years old.
تزوجت في عمر الثامنة عشر
And you know what?
أتعلمون؟
I knew, I knew
أعرف، أعرف
that I was born for more than this.
لقد خلقت لأشياء أكثر من ذلك
And right at the point in the story of my life I had a choice.
والحق يقال أنه كان لدي الاختيار في حياتي
I could let all these things push me down
كان بإمكاني قول أن كل تلك الأشياء دمرتني
and I could let all my ideas die inside of me.
وجعل كل تلك الأفكار تموت بداخلي
I could just say, you know, life is too hard to change the world.
أستطيع فقط أن أقول، إن الحياة صعبة جداً لتغيير العالم.
It's just too tough.
إنها فقط قاسية جداً.
But I chose a different story for my life.
ولكنني أختار قصة مختلفة لحياتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Don't you know it?
ألا تعرفونها؟
And so I feel like there's people in this room --
و لذلك أشعر مثل يوجد أُناس في هذه الغرفة..
you got those little Suavitos baking spices
أنت تمتلك هذه توابل الخبز
and you're just like, "You know, It's not that big a deal."
وأنت فقط مثل، أتعلم، أنها ليست بالأمر العظيم."
"It's really not the whole world I can change."
"إنها حقاً ليس أنني أستطيع تغيير العالم كله."
But you know, you can change your world.
ولكن أتعلم، تستطيع تغيير عالمك.
You can change your life.
تستطيع تغيير حياتك.
You can change the world that you have control over,
تستطيع تغيير العالم الذي تتحكم فيه،
you can change your sphere.
تستطيع تغيير مكانك.
I want to encourage you to do that.
أريد تشجيعك لفعل ذلك.
Because you know what?
لأنك أتعلم ماذا؟
The future isn't a place that we're going to go.
ليس المستقبل بمكان سنذهب إليه.
It's a place that you get to create.
وإنما مكان ستخلقه.
I want to thank you. Bless you. God bless you.
أريد أن أشكركم. بارك الله عليكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)